Finding Aid for Eric R. Wolf Papers, 1939-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Early/Unpublished Writing
  - American Historical Association Conference, "Progress and Paradox in Latin American History," 1975 (Box 7)
  - Conference on International Institute of Peasant and Agrarian Studies, Manchester 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Conference on Rural Economy and Society in Contemporary Eastern Europe, Bellagio, "The Second Serfdom..."1980 (Box 8)
  - Commencement Address, Lehman College, City University of New York, "The Myth of Juan Valdez," 1986 (Box 8)
  - Honoring Colleagues
    - Essay for Angel Palerm, "Culture and Ideology," 1982 (Box 8)
    - For Robert M. Netting, "Ecology and History," 1996 plus correspondence, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Article for Pedro Armillas Garcia, Archaeology of Ancient Mexico and Central America 1994 (Box 8)
    - AAA Session for Joan Vincent, Washington, DC 1995 (Box 8)
    - AAA Conference, "Capitalism, Nation-Formation and Ethnicity," 1987 (Box 8)
  - Lecture at DePaul University, "Culture and the Forces of the World," plus Charles Strain Response 1988 (Box 8)
  - European Association of Social Anthropologists Conference, Prague, Wolf on the Usefulness of Marxism in Anthropology 1992 (Box 8)
  - Plenary Session, ICAES, Mexico City, "Societies, Evolution and Globalization," 1993, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, "Unforeseen Americas..." 1996 (Box 8)
  - Seminar, Amsterdam 1997 (Box 8)
  - NYAS, "Anthropology and the Academy: Historical Reflections," 1998 (Box 8)
- Courses
  The Courses series, 1953-1991 (1 linear ft.), documents a number of the courses Wolf taught as a professor. This series is arranged by institution, and includes syllabi as well as some lecture outlines Wolf used in the courses he taught. A number of particularly outstanding papers written by students at the University of Michigan are included as well.
  - Anthropology 12: Indians of Mexico and Guatemala (Box 8)
  - Anthropology 361: Ethnology of Middle America (Box 8)
  - University of Illinois
    - Anthropology 103: Introduction to Anthropology: The Growth of Culture circa 1953 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 107: Introduction to Anthropology circa 1953 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 260: Primitive Society circa 1953 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 362: Patterns of Folk and Peasant Cultures 1953 (Box 8)
  - University of Virginia 1955-1958 (Box 8)
  - Columbia University 1959 (Box 8)
  - University of Chicago 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - University of Michigan
    - "A Guide to Beginning Graduate Studies in Anthropology," 1969 (Box 8)
    - Department of Anthropology Guide 1970-1971 (Box 8)
    - Proposed Course on Medieval Society and Culture 1962-1963 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 101 circa 1963 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology of Underdevelopment circa 1970 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 222: Introduction to Primitive Culture 1962, 1968, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 305: Marxism and Anthropology 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 417: Contemporary Latin American Civilization 1968-1970 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 556/Sociology 656: Peasant Culture and Society 1961-1963, 1966, 1969, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 580/Sociology 480: Personality and Culture 1962-1964, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 657: Mediterranean Anthropology 1970 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 805: Readings in Ethnology (Box 8)
    - Student Papers
      - Barrett, Richard, "Caciquismo in Spain," 1966 (Box 8)
      - Christian, William
        - "Forbidden Fruit: A Worldview in Process," 1969 (Box 8)
        - "Shrine Location in Spain..." (Box 8)
      - Hansen, Ed (Box 8)
      - Isazevich, Abraham, "Emigrantes, Cubas y Solteronas en España," 1970 (Box 8)
      - McConochie, Roger, "Pfelders: Village in a Small World," 1969 (Box 8)
      - Meeropol, Robert
        - "The Decline of Spain," 1970 (Box 8)
        - "Marxist Anthropology and Cultural Materialism: A Somewhat Synthesis," 1969 (Box 8)
        - Preliminary Exam Paper Proposal 1971 (Box 8)
      - Nichamin, J., "Rural Class Structure in France" (Box 8)
      - Potter, Paul, "Patron Client Relationships in the Mediterranean," 1963 (Box 8)
      - Reiter, Randy
        - "Boules: A Public Relations Game," 1971 (Box 8)
        - "Boules and Public Relations in a Provencal Village," 1971 (Box 8)
        - "Male-Female Relations in the Mediterranean," 1970 (Box 8)
      - Roby, James Joseph 1969 (Box 8)
      - Rosenberg, Harriet, Randy Reiter and Rayna Reiter, "Rural Workers in French Alpine Tourism" (Box 8)
      - Schneider, Pete & Jane, "Ecological History of the Protection Racket in Sicily" (Box 8)
      - Tudiver, Sari, "Towards Some Urbanrural Boundaries," 1970 (Box 8)
      - Yoon, Soon (Box 8)
      - Young, Loren, "Politics, Economics, and Mediterranean Transhumance," 1970 (Box 8)
  - University of Utah 1986 (Box 8)
  - City University of New York
    - ANC 100 1971, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Introduction to Anthropology (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 238 1973-1990 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology 338 1979-1992 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology, Assorted 1977-1979 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology U700: The Unity of Anthropology, Course Development 1987 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology U701, Notes 1981 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology U703.02: Contemporary Anthropological Theory 1977, 1979, 1983, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology U703: History of Theory 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Anthropology U732.02: Ethnology and Ethnography of Mesoamerica 1976, 1978, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U732.02: Ethnology and Ethnography of South America 1986, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U733: Ethnology and Ethnography of Mesoamerica and the Caribbean 1983, 1985, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U807: Seminar -- Ethnography and Theory 1989, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U808: Political Economy 1988 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U810.03: Seminar on Ideology 1984, 1987, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U811.3: Seminar on Peasantries and Working Classes 1982 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U820.04: Anthropology and the Study of the African Diaspora 1981-1982 (Box 9)
    - Anthropology U824.05: Seminar in Latin American Anthropology 1979 (Box 9)
    - Curriculum Ideas (Box 9)
    - Program Seminar, Religion (Box 9)
    - Program Seminar, State Formation (Box 9)
  - Mexico City: Peasant Movements (Box 9)
- Lectures
  The Lectures series, 1961-1998 (1.5 linear ft.), contains the text and details of public lectures Wolf gave around the world over a span of almost four decades. While not a comprehensive listing of the large number of speaking arrangement in which Wolf engaged, the texts of these lectures are representative and provide insight into Wolf's evolving perspective and his public involvement.
  - 1961
    - "Kinship and Interpersonal Communication in the Upper Anaunia," American Anthropological Association (Box 9)
  - 1972
    - Seminar on the Valley of Mexico, School of American Research (includes 2 reels of magnetic audio tape) (Box 9)
  - 1978
    - "The Mills of Inequality," Burge Wartenstein Symposium: Social Inequality: Comparative and Developmental Approaches (Box 9)
  - 1979
    - Conference on Religion and Religious Movements in the Mediterranean Area, Free University, Amsterdam (Box 9)
  - 1980
    - Colloquium on Agrarian Class Formation in the World System, Duke University (Box 9)
  - 1982
    - "Knowledge and Monkey Business," Commencement Address, Lehman College, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "The Making of Working Classes: An Anthropological View," Hartwick College (Box 9)
    - Conference on New Approaches to Puerto Rican History, Lehman College, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "Culture: Panacea or Problem?" NEAA 1982 (Box 9)
  - 1983
    - Lansdowne Visitor Lectures, University of Victoria (Box 9)
    - "The People Without History," Plenary Session, University Faculty Senate, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "The Vicissitudes of the Closed Corporate Peasant Community" 1983 (Box 9)
  - 1984
    - "Beyond Eurocentrism," Comparative and International Studies, University of California, Santa Cruz (Box 9)
    - "Cycles of Violence: The Anthropology of Peace and War," Notre Dame University (Box 9)
    - "Ethnicity and the Vicissitudes of Labor," American-Society Symposium on Contemporary Ethnic Processes in the USA and the USSR (Box 9)
    - "Jumbo-History and Normal Anthropology," Committee on Historical Studies, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "The Peasant Wars: Engels and Social History," Engels: Beyond the Origins: A Colloquium, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "Rethinking Culture," New York Academy of Sciences, Section of Anthropology (Box 9)
    - New Perspectives on Caribbean Studies, Toward the 21st Century Conference, Hunter College, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - Sociologisch Tijdschrift, Amsterdam (Box 9)
  - 1985
    - "Core and Periphery in the World System: In History and in the Present," Polytechnic Institute of New York (Box 9)
    - "Inventing Society," Johns Hopkins University (Box 9)
    - Colloquium on National Character, University of Nijmegen (Box 9)
    - Introductory Queries Roundtable on Changing Patterns of Class Formation, City University of New York, Graduate Center (Box 9)
    - University of Oklahoma at Norman (Box 9)
  - 1986
    - "Indigenous Peoples of the Americas: The Maya, Aztec, and Inca Cultures of Mexico and Peru," New York University (Box 9)
  - 1987
    - "Europe and the People Without History," El Colegio de Mexico (Box 9)
    - "The Global Connection: World Capitalism and Local Life," Social Science Symposium, DePauw University (Box 9)
    - "In Search of Culture," Washington University in St. Louis (Box 9)
    - "Thinking about Central America," Humanities Colloquia, Lehman College, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - Conference on Religious Regimes and State Formation, Amsterdam (Box 9)
    - Society for Applied Anthropology, Oaxaca, Mexico (Box 9)
  - 1988
    - Guest Lecture, Anthropology U702: The Anthropology of Complex Societies, City University of New York (Box 9)
    - "Ethnicity and Nationhood", International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Zagreeb (Box 9)
  - 1989
    - "Facing Power: Old Insights, New Questions," Distinguished Lecture, American Anthropological Association (Box 9)
    - "Shaking the Money Tree" (Box 9)
  - 1990
    - "The Anthropology of Complex Societies," Institut für Ethnologie, Bern (Box 9)
    - "Freedom and Freedoms: Anthropological Perspectives," 29th TB Davie Memorial Lecture, University of Cape Town (Box 9)
    - Anthropology Society, Queens College (Box 9)
  - 1991
    - Seminaro Mesoamérica y el Area Andina, Centro de Investigaciones y Estudias Superiores en Antropología Social (Box 9)
  - 1992
    - "Aspects of the German Catastrophe," City University of New York, Graduate Center (Box 9)
    - "Global Perspectives in Anthropology: Problems and Prospects," International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Mexico City (Box 9)
    - "Perilous Ideas: Race, Culture, People," Inaugural Sidney Mintz Lecture, Johns Hopkins University
      - English version (Box 9)
      - German translation (Box 9)
    - Seminar on Thailand Controversy (Cassette tape) (Box 9)
    - "Unforeseen Americas", Opening Address, Columbus Quincentenary Commemoration, Herbert Lehman College, City University of New York (Box 9)
  - 1993
    - "Explaining Mesoamerica", Vienna (Box 10)
    - "Thoughts on Boyhood in Vienna" and Dostal Lecture (Box 10)
    - "La Frontiera Nascosta: A Retrospective," 4th Meeting of the Permanent Seminar on Alpine Anthropology, Museo degli usi e costumi della gente Trentina (Box 10)
    - "Reflections on the State of the Discipline," Graduate Center, City University of New York (Box 10)
    - New York Academy of Sciences, Anthropology Section (Box 10)
  - 1994
    - "The State Under Siege: Comments," American Anthropological Association (Box 10)
    - Western Michigan University (Box 10)
  - 1995
    - "Big Systems and Micro-Scenarios," Universität van Amsterdam (Box 10)
    - "Home-Made Models and Jumbo Theory: A View From Anthropology," New School for Social Research (Box 10)
    - American Anthropological Association (Papers on the Influence of Joan Vincent) (Box 10)
  - 1997
    - "Cognizing Cognized Models," Society for Applied Anthropology (Box 10)
    - "Envisioning Power: Report on an Inquiry," Amsterdam (Box 10)
  - 1998
    - "Anthropology Among the Powers," European Association of Social Anthropologists Conference, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Publications
  The Publications series, 1953-2008 (1.2 linear ft.), includes correspondence and reviewers' comments related to a number of Wolf's published works, as well as several unpublished pieces written in honor of friends and fellow anthropologists Elman Service and Roy Rappaport. Outlines of textbooks that never came to fruition are also included. These documents provide some context for understanding peer's thinking and reception of Wolf's work.
  - Books
    - Afterwards and Forwards
      - Afterward, Bara 1998 (Box 10)
      - Forwards, Assorted, Scattered dates (Box 10)
    - Anthology of Wolf's work 1984 (Box 10)
    - Anthropology 1974 (Box 10)
    - "Envisioning Power"
      - Correspondence 1988-1996 (Box 10)
      - Feedback from Jane Schneider circa 1996 (Box 10)
      - Manuscript Reading Reports 1997 (Box 10)
      - Title Suggestions (Box 10)
    - "Europe and the People Without History"
      - Readers' Comments (1980) (Box 10)
      - Notes and Correspondence 1981-2001 (Scattered) (Box 10)
      - Reviews 1982-1998 (Box 10)
    - "Hidden Frontier" (Box 10)
    - "Human Conditions in Latin America" (Box 10)
    - "Pathways of Power", Early Conceptions 1998 (Box 10)
    - "Pathways of Power" 2001 (Box 10)
    - "Peasants", Reviewers' Comments and translation agreements 1977 (Box 10)
    - "Peasant Wars of the Twentieth Century" (Box 10)
    - Photos (Box 10)
    - "Religion and Power" (Box 10)
    - "Sons of the Shaking Earth" (Box 10)
    - "Valley of Mexico" (Box 10)
  - Book Reviews
    - Reviews of books (Box 10)
    - Reviews of manuscripts (Box 10)
  - Exhibition Catalog (Box 11)
  - Honoring Colleagues
    - Palerm, Angel
      - "Culture and Ideology" (Box 11)
      - Obituary (Box 11)
    - Rappaport, Roy: Obituary (Box 11)
    - Thrupp, Sylvia: Honoring upon retirement (Box 11)
  - Journal Articles
    - "American Anthropologists and American Society," Concepts and Assumptions in Contemporary Anthropology, 1969 (Box 11)
    - "La Formación de la nación," Ciencias Sociales, 1953 (Box 11)
    - "The Peasant War in Germany" (Box 11)
    - "They Divide and Subdivide..." New York Times, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Collected
      - 1957-1961 (Box 11)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 11)
      - Misrepresentation 1998 (Box 11)
      - Undated (Box 11)
  - Reprints Annotated by Others, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Review Articles by Others 1993-2008 (Box 11)
  - Reviews of "Europe and the People Without History" 1983-1984 (Box 11)
  - Unpublished
    - "Introduction to Cultural Anthropology", Textbook (Box 11)
    - "Perilous Ideas, Race, Culture, People," Current Anthropology, 1992-1993 (Box 11)
    - "Ideas and Power," Festschrift for Elman Service 1985 (Box 11)
    - Textbook with Archie Singham (Box 11)
- Notes
  The Notes series, 1946-1950 and undated (1 linear ft.), consists of two subseries. Graduate School Notes contains notes Wolf took in his graduate school years at Columbia University. Filtered through the lens of Wolf, these notes provide a view into anthropological instruction of the late 1940s, and many of the lectures were given by prominent anthropologists, including Alfred Kroeber, Ruth Benedict, and Margaret Mead. The second subseries includes undated notes, possibly used for courses and lectures.
  - General
    - Maya undated (Box 11)
    - Mesoamerican Codices undated (Box 11)
    - Study of Meaning lecture 1974 (Box 11)
    - Study group on Long Distance Trade 1975 (Box 11)
    - Tikopia undated (Box 11)
  - Graduate School
    - "Africa", 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "America," 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "America," 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Asia," 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Benedict," 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Economics," 1949-1950 (Box 11)
    - "Europe General," 1947 (Box 11)
    - "Human Biology," 1946-1947, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - "Language," 1946 (Box 12)
    - "N. America," 1949, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - "Theory I," 1946-1949 (Box 12)
    - "Theory II," 1946-1979 (Box 12)
- Political Activities
  Political Activities, 1965-1984 (0.3 linear ft.), provides a sampling of the political situations in which Wolf was active. Wolf was a key figure in the organization of Vietnam era Teach-ins, as well as participating in other anti-war activities. As a member of the American Anthropological Association's (AAA) Ethics Committee, Wolf played a key role in what became known as the Thailand Controversy; questionable research activities being conducted by anthropologists in that country.
  - Central America 1983-1984 (Box 12)
  - China Conference 1966 (Box 12)
  - Thailand Controversy 1969-1972
    - Background (Box 12)
    - Fallout (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, with and regarding, Moreman, Phillips, Picker, and Sharp (Box 12)
    - "Student Mobilizer" (Box 12)
    - November 1971 meeting (Box 12)
  - Vietnam
    - Activism 1968-1971 (Box 12)
    - Alternative Perspectives Conference 1965 (Box 12)
    - National Teach-in May 1965 (Box 12)
    - University of Michigan Teach-in March 1965 (Box 12)
- Other materials
  The Other Materials series (2.0 linear ft.), also added to the collection in 2011, consists of one box of personal calendars and one box containing a collection of index cards, in alphabetical order, representing books and other materials read by Wolf.
  - Personal Calendars (pocket and desk size) (Box 13)
  - Bibliographical Cards (lists of readings) (Box 14)